{
  "Application Process": {
    "deadline": "March 1st (applies to both domestic and international students)",
    "statement_of_purpose": "No specific formatting requirements",
    "interview": {
      "required": true,
      "format": "online technical interview with faculty",
      "topics": ["linear algebra", "statistics", "programming"]
    },
    "test_scores": {
      "GRE_GMAT": "not required but can be optionally submitted"
    },
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "Is the application deadline the same for international students?",
        "answer": "Yes. This also applies to international students."
      },
      {
        "question": "Are there specific formatting requirements for the statement of purpose?",
        "answer": "We don't have any specific requirements for the statement formatting."
      },
      {
        "question": "Is it possible to defer admission?",
        "answer": "Regretfully, we do not defer admissions offers. However, applicants who have been admitted once are likely to be admitted again in the subsequent year, should they need to turn down the offer and reapply."
      },
      {
        "question": "How does completing prerequisite courses after applying affect admission decisions?",
        "answer": "Completing your prerequisite courses by April will not negatively impact your application. You can proceed with your application, but it's important to note that any admission decision will be contingent upon the successful completion of these courses. I recommend submitting transcripts or proof of enrollment for these courses along with your application and ensuring all final transcripts are submitted as soon as the courses are completed."
      },
      {
        "question": "Are GRE scores required for admission?",
        "answer": "The program does not require a GRE or GMAT test. If you have already taken either of these exams and wish to include the scores in your application, you have the choice to upload them. Nevertheless, an English Language exam score (TOEFL - 90, IELTS - 6.5, Duolingo - 115, or PTE - 61) is mandatory for international applicants."
      },
      {
        "question": "Can I submit my application before receiving all test scores?",
        "answer": "The program does not require a GRE or GMAT test. If you have already taken either of these exams and wish to include the scores in your application, you have the choice to upload them. Nevertheless, an English Language exam score is mandatory for international applicants."
      },
      {
        "question": "Is an interview required for admission?",
        "answer": "Yes, all applicants must complete an online technical interview with a faculty member from the admissions committee."
      },
      {
        "question": "How should I prepare for the admission interview?",
        "answer": "The interview will cover key prerequisite subjects, including linear algebra, statistics, and programming. It is also an opportunity to ask questions about the program."
      },
      {
        "question": "What courses are offered in the program?",
        "answer": "Core Programming and Computing: Courses like MSDS 501 (Computation for Data Science), MSDS 689 (Data Structures and Algorithms), and MSDS 694 (Distributed Computing) build your technical foundation. Statistics and Mathematics: MSDS 504 (Review Probability and Stats), MSDS 601 (Linear Regression Analysis), and MSDS 604 (Time Series Analysis) cover the statistical underpinnings. Machine Learning and AI: Courses like MSDS 621 (Intro to Machine Learning), MSDS 630 (Advanced Machine Learning), and MSDS 634 (Deep Learning) provide both theoretical understanding and practical applications. Data Management: MSDS 691 (Relational Databases), MSDS 692 (Data Acquisition), and MSDS 697 (Distributed Data Systems) cover how to work with data at scale. Professional Skills: MSDS 610 (Communication for Data Science), MSDS 603 (Data Science Entrepreneurship), and MSDS 633 (Ethics in Data Science) develop critical workplace skills. Hands-on Experience: The program includes a four-part practicum series (MSDS 605, 625, 627, 632) where you will ll work on real-world projects. Specialized Topics: MSDS 631 (Special Topics) and MSDS 699 (Machine Learning Laboratory) allow for exploration of cutting-edge areas."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Admission Requirements": {
    "prerequisite_courses": {
      "required": [
        "Inferential Statistics",
        "Linear Algebra",
        "Programming"
      ],
      "recommended": [
        "Calculus",
        "Data Structures"
      ]
    },
    "conditions": {
      "formal_coursework": "preferred for prerequisites",
      "offer_contingencies": [
        "completing in-progress prerequisites",
        "bachelor's degree completion"
      ],
      "GPA_evaluation": "only at time of admission review"
    },
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "What conditions are included in admission offers for current undergraduate students?",
        "answer": "The only condition there could be is completion of an in progress prerequisite, and of course, a conferral of bachelor's degree. GPA is only evaluated at the time of admission review."
      },
      {
        "question": "Can I apply without formal prerequisite coursework?",
        "answer": "We do prefer to see formal coursework in all three areas of prerequisites. It would be very unlikely for a candidate to be admitted if they lacked such courses in all three subject areas."
      },
      {
        "question": "How can applicants from non-technical backgrounds succeed in this program?",
        "answer": "We have students from a wide range of backgrounds, and welcome any major. However, given the highly accelerated pace of the program, it is important that students have a solid grasp of statistics and programming and a decent background in calculus and linear algebra in order to do well. Our website includes a list of preapproved online courses for each prerequisite. This list is not exhaustive, any course that's taken for a letter grade and includes a proctored exam will suffice."
      },
      {
        "question": "What are the prerequisite requirements for the program?",
        "answer": "We require three prerequisite courses: Inferential Statistics, Linear Algebra, and a Programming course. Additionally, we strongly recommend courses in Calculus and Data Structures. If you have questions about the eligibility of courses you have taken or plan to take, please view the list of key concepts to understand for each subject on our How to Apply page."
      },
      {
        "question": "Are certificate courses accepted for prerequisite requirements?",
        "answer": "The Date Institute courses are accepted because they are developed by our MSDS faculty, these certificate courses may be applied towards the MSDS prerequisite course requirements."
      },
      {
        "question": "Can I apply without all prerequisite skills?",
        "answer": "You must have completed all required prerequisite courses before the start of the program. This is an accelerated master's program and there is no time to take extra courses. You may apply with courses in progress provided that they will be completed by the time the program begins."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Financial Aid & Scholarships": {
    "program_scholarships": {
      "consideration": "automatic for admitted candidates",
      "coverage": "maximum 20% of tuition",
      "application": "no separate application required"
    },
    "restrictions": {
      "double_dons": "cannot be combined with other USF scholarships",
      "refugee_grants": "no specific grants, external funding recommended"
    },
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "What financial assistance options are available for graduate students?",
        "answer": "All admitted candidates will be considered for program scholarships, which will be detailed in the admission letter. No separate application is required. However, please note that our scholarships cover a maximum of 20% of tuition, so students will need to secure additional funding sources for the program. You can check the Program Overview and FAQs for additional information."
      },
      {
        "question": "What financial aid options are available for international students?",
        "answer": "Unfortunately the Double Dons award cannot be stacked with another USF scholarship award, so external scholarships or private loans would be the other financing options for international students."
      },
      {
        "question": "Are there specific financial grants for refugees?",
        "answer": "While USF does not have a specific grant exclusively for refugees, you may want to explore external funding opportunities, as well as federal financial aid options, if eligible. Also, I encourage you to reach out to the Financial Aid Office at financialaid@usfca.edu for guidance other funding resources that might apply to your situation."
      },
      {
        "question": "How do I apply for scholarships in the program?",
        "answer": "All admitted candidates will be considered for program scholarships, which will be detailed in the admission letter. No separate application is required. However, please note that our scholarships cover a maximum of 20% of tuition, so students will need to secure additional funding sources for the program."
      },
      {
        "question": "Are scholarships based on academic and professional achievements?",
        "answer": "For scholarships, all admitted students are automatically considered for program scholarships, which will be detailed in the admission letter. No separate application is required. Please note that scholarships cover a maximum of 20% of tuition, so students must secure additional funding to support their studies."
      }
    ]
  },
  "International Students": {
    "STEM_designation": {
      "status": true,
      "OPT": "24-month extension after initial 12-month OPT"
    },
    "language_requirements": {
      "TOEFL": 90,
      "IELTS": 6.5,
      "Duolingo": 115,
      "PTE": 61,
      "exemptions": "bachelor's/master's degree from US or exempted countries"
    },
    "financial_documentation": "Can submit application without complete Certificate of Finance if applying for loans",
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "Is this program STEM designated for OPT extension purposes?",
        "answer": "Yes, the program is STEM designated, with the 24 month OPT extension after the initial 12 month OPT."
      },
      {
        "question": "How can international students fulfill financial documentation requirements for visa applications?",
        "answer": "If you plan to finance your education with a loan, you will need to obtain a letter from your bank stating that they will provide a loan for the needed amount if you are admitted. Upload this letter to the certification of finances section of the application. If you are unable to provide a letter, please contact asapplication@usfca.edu for other options."
      },
      {
        "question": "Can financial documentation be submitted after admission?",
        "answer": "Yes we can move your application forward for review without the complete Certificate of Finance if you are planning to apply for a loan and require the admission letter for your loan application. Please upload any financial documents that you have into the Certificate of Finance section of the application, as well as a statement explaining that you intend to apply for a student loan but require the admission letter for your loan application."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Enrollment Process": {
    "documentation": {
      "enrollment": "No green card or documentation required",
      "practicum": "Companies may require SSN/work authorization"
    },
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "What documentation is required for enrollment after acceptance?",
        "answer": "The university will not ask for a green card or other documentation to complete your enrollment. However, once the students are matched to their practicum company, the company's HR may require social security card and/or proof of work authorization as part of their onboarding."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Program Structure": {
    "duration": {
      "standard": "one year, full-time",
      "extended": "18 months with Data Engineering concentration",
      "data_engineering_details": {
        "description": "The Data Engineering Concentration builds on the curriculum of the MSDS program, focusing on a comprehensive theoretical and technical understanding of statistical analysis, machine learning, and systems to deploy and maintain a life cycle of data and models.",
        "timeline": "During the spring and summer, students complete the core MSDS curriculum, while the second year fall semester is dedicated to Data Engineering concentration courses.",
        "schedule": "Courses meet twice a week in the afternoons and evenings, allowing students to focus on their post-graduation job search or work part-time.",
        "international_students": "International students have the option to do part-time work or an internship through Pre-Completion Optional Practical Training (OPT) while enrolled in the Data Engineering concentration."
      }
    },
    "cohort_size": "approximately 90 students",
    "class_format": {
      "sections": "multiple sections to keep sizes small",
      "teaching_assistants": "none for lectures or discussions",
      "start_date": "early July each year"
    },
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "When does the program start and what is the application deadline?",
        "answer": "Thank you for your interest in our program. The Master of Science in Data Science (MSDS) is a full-time, one-year program. The 35-unit program starts in early July each year, and it's important to note that admissions are only available in the summer."
      },
      {
        "question": "How long does the program take to complete?",
        "answer": "The MSDS program is designed to be completed in 12 months of full-time study. Additionally, there is an option to extend the program by one semester (totaling 18 months) to concentrate on Data Engineering."
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the class size and teaching structure?",
        "answer": "Our 2024–2025 cohort will be approximately 90 students in size. In most classes, we run lectures in two or more sections to keep class sizes small. There are no teaching assistants leading class lectures or class discussions in our program."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Program Overview": {
    "name": "Master of Science in Data Science (MSDS)",
    "focus": [
      "technical expertise",
      "business acumen",
      "analytics",
      "machine learning",
      "deep learning",
      "cloud computing"
    ],
    "key_feature": "nine-month practicum with real companies",
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "What is the MSDS program?",
        "answer": "The Master of Science in Data Science (MSDS) program at the University of San Francisco (USF) is a full-time, one-year program designed to equip students with the technical expertise and business acumen necessary for successful careers in data science."
      },
      {
        "question": "What are the benefits of the MSDS program?",
        "answer": "The Master of Science in Data Science (MSDS) program at the University of San Francisco (USF) is a full-time, one-year program designed to equip students with the technical expertise and business acumen necessary for successful careers in data science. USF's MSDS program offers a rigorous curriculum that integrates courses in analytics, machine learning, deep learning, cloud computing, and more. A distinctive feature is the nine-month practicum, where students collaborate with real companies on data science projects, providing hands-on experience that is highly valued by employers."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Tuition & Costs": {
    "tuition": {
      "cost_per_unit": 1695,
      "total_units": 35,
      "academic_year": "2025-2026"
    },
    "additional_costs": [
      "housing",
      "meals",
      "books",
      "supplies",
      "personal expenses"
    ],
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "What is the cost of the program?",
        "answer": "The estimated cost of the MS in Data Science is $1,695 per unit for the 2025-2026 academic year, with a minimum of 35 units required to be completed each academic year. Students typically take an average of 35 units each academic year. A total of 35 units are required for the degree. Program fees are subject to adjustment annually."
      },
      {
        "question": "What additional expenses should students budget for beyond tuition?",
        "answer": "Beyond tuition, students should budget for housing, meals, books, supplies, and other personal expenses. Costs for housing and meals can vary, and students should consult the university's estimated cost of attendance for detailed information."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Program Preparation": {
    "recommended_background": [
      "mathematics",
      "statistics",
      "computer science"
    ],
    "experience": "prior data science experience beneficial but not required",
    "prerequisites": "must complete before program start",
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "How can I succeed in the program without prior data science experience?",
        "answer": "While prior experience in data science is beneficial, the MSDS program provides a comprehensive curriculum that covers foundational to advanced topics. Prospective students need to have  are encouraged to have a strong background in mathematics, statistics, or computer science to facilitate their success in the program."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Faculty & Research": {
    "leadership": {
      "program_director": {
        "name": "Shan Wang",
        "email": "swang151@usfca.edu",
        "description": "Dr. Shan Wang is the program director and an assistant professor in the MS in Data Science program at the University of San Francisco. Her research interests include nonparametric statistics, biomedical data science, and utilizing data-driven methods to address social and environmental problems.",
        "education": "PhD, Statistics, Purdue University, 2015; BS, Mathematics, Fudan University, 2009"
      },
      "administrative_director": {
        "name": "Aija Tapaninen",
        "email": "atapaninen@usfca.edu",
        "description": "Aija Tapaninen has been with USF since 2014. Prior to joining the MSDS program team, she has held positions in the Strategic Enrollment Management division and at the School of Management, working with the campus community on a range of topics related to graduate student education. Before USF, Aija was in graduate admissions and student affairs at UC Berkeley and UCLA.",
        "education": "University of San Francisco, MBA, 2017; University of San Francisco, MA in Organization & Leadership, 2010; San Francisco State University, BA in Intercultural Communication, 2005"
      }
    },
    "full_time_faculty": [
      {
        "name": "David Guy Brizan",
        "email": "dgbrizan@usfca.edu",
        "office_location": "Harney Science Center 404",
        "description": "David is an associate professor at the University of San Francisco. His research interests are natural language processing, machine learning, and databases — specifically on the personal and cultural/demographic information transmitted during speech and typing.",
        "education": "PhD, Computer Science, CUNY Graduate Center (candidate); MS Computer Science, San Francisco State University; BS Computer & Information Science, Brooklyn College",
        "expertise": ["Speech Processing", "Applications of Machine Learning"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Cody Carroll",
        "email": "cjcarroll@usfca.edu",
        "description": "Cody Carroll is an assistant professor with joint appointments in the Department of Mathematics and Statistics and the Master's in Data Science program (MSDS).",
        "education": "UC Davis, PhD in Statistics, 2021; UC Davis, MS in Statistics, 2017; UT Austin, BS in Mathematics, 2014",
        "expertise": ["Time warping & curve registration", "Multivariate functional data", "Statistical consulting", "Communication through statistics"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Mahesh Chaudhari",
        "email": "mchaudhari@usfca.edu",
        "office_location": "101 Howard, Room 524",
        "description": "Mahesh Chaudhari is an assistant professor in the MS in Data Science program at the University of San Francisco. His research interests include databases, data engineering and cloud computing.",
        "education": "Arizona State University, PhD in Computer Science, 2011; Mississippi State University, MS in Computer Science 2003; University of Mumbai, Mumbai, India, BE in Computer Science and Engineering, 1999",
        "expertise": ["Data engineering", "Cloud computing", "Building autonomous data processing infrastructure"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Robert Clements",
        "email": "rclements@usfca.edu",
        "description": "Robert Clements is an assistant professor in the MS in Data Science program and the Director of the Center for AI and Data Ethics.",
        "education": "UCLA, PhD in Statistics, 2011; UCLA, MS in Statistics, 2009; Humboldt State University, BA in Mathematics, 2006",
        "expertise": ["Machine Learning", "MLOps", "Applied Statistics", "AI and Data Ethics"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Stephen Devlin",
        "email": "smdevlin@usfca.edu",
        "office_location": "Harney Science Center 122C",
        "description": "Stephen Devlin is a Professor in the Department of Mathematics and Statistics and the Master's in Data Science program (MSDS).",
        "education": "PhD, Mathematics, University of Maryland, 2001",
        "expertise": ["Pure and applied mathematics"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Mustafa Hajij",
        "email": "mhajij@usfca.edu",
        "description": "Mustafa Hajij is an assistant professor at the MSDS program at University of San Francisco.",
        "education": "Louisiana State University, PhD in Mathematics; Louisiana State University, MS in Computer Science; Jordan University for Science and Technology, MS in Mathematics; Damascus University, BS in Mathematics",
        "expertise": ["Deep Learning", "Algorithms"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Yannet Interian",
        "email": "yinterian@usfca.edu",
        "office_location": "101 Howard, 605",
        "description": "Yannet is an associate professor in the Master's in Data Science program, and her research interests lie in the application of machine learning and deep learning to medical data.",
        "education": "Cornell University, PhD in Applied Mathematics, 2006",
        "expertise": ["machine learning", "deep learning", "medical data"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Victor Palacios",
        "email": "vpalacios@usfca.edu",
        "description": "Victor received his master's degree in data science from the University of San Francisco and is currently working in the same field at the University of San Francisco as the Director of Data Science Partnerships.",
        "education": "University of San Francisco, MS in Data Science, 2021; Nagoya University, MS in Information Science, 2015; UC Berkeley, BA in Japanese, 2011",
        "expertise": ["Natural language processing", "Deception"]
      },
      {
        "name": "James Wilson",
        "email": "jdwilson4@usfca.edu",
        "office_location": "Harney Science Center Office 121A",
        "description": "James is a statistics and data science educator, researcher, mentor, and enthusiast. His research merges computational statistics, random graph theory, and machine learning to provide interpretable machinery to model, explore, and analyze complex interacting and imaging systems.",
        "education": "PhD, Statistics and Operations Research, University of North Carolina, 2015; MS, Mathematical Sciences, Clemson University, 2010; BS, Mathematics and Chemistry, Campbell University, 2008",
        "expertise": ["computational statistics", "random graph theory", "machine learning"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Diane Woodbridge",
        "email": "dwoodbridge@usfca.edu",
        "office_location": "101 Howard 606",
        "description": "Diane Woodbridge is an associate professor in the MS in Data Science program at the University of San Francisco. Her research interests include scalable database management systems, data fusion, and machine learning focusing on remote health monitoring (IoT in Healthcare).",
        "education": "PhD, Computer Science, University of California, Los Angeles; MS, Computer Science, University of California, Los Angeles; BS, Computer Science and Engineering, Sogang University, South Korea",
        "expertise": ["Scalable database systems", "Data fusion", "Machine learning for IoT in Healthcare"]
      }
    ],
    "part_time_faculty": [
      {
        "name": "Sundar Dorai-Raj",
        "email": "sdorairaj@usfca.edu",
        "office_location": "101 Howard St.",
        "description": "Sundar Dorai-Raj has been a data scientist at Google since 2009. He has spent most of his career working on Ads products, from YouTube Ads, where he helped launch YouTube's first skippable ad format, to Brand Lift and Google Analytics.",
        "education": "Virginia Tech, PhD in Statistics, 2001; Virginia Tech, MS in Statistics, 1999; University of Alabama, MA in Applied Math, 1997; University of Alabama, BS in Applied Math, 1995",
        "expertise": ["A/B testing", "statistical modeling", "machine learning"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Mark Graves",
        "email": "mgraves@usfca.edu",
        "description": "Mark Graves has fifteen years experience in developing software, informatics, and data science solutions for healthcare and the pharmaceutical industry.",
        "education": "Graduate Theological Union/Jesuit School of Theology, MA in Systematic & Philosophical Theology, 2005; University of Michigan, PhD in Computer Science, 1993; Georgia Institute of Technology, MS in Computer Science, 1989",
        "expertise": ["Artificial Intelligence", "Natural Language Processing", "Moral psychology & well-being", "Religion, science & technology"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Stephen Hsu",
        "email": "sjhsu@dons.usfca.edu",
        "description": "Stephen Hsu is a Solutions Architect helping companies end-to-end data projects with experience deriving insights from data to augment decisions in industries such as finance, retail, and healthcare.",
        "education": "USF MS in Data Science, 2018; UC Berkeley, BA in Cognitive Science, 2017",
        "expertise": ["Data Engineering", "Data Science", "Machine Learning", "Data Visualizations"]
      },
      {
        "name": "Nico Thiebaut",
        "email": "nthiebaut@usfca.edu",
        "description": "Drawn to theoretical physics, Nico Thiebaut became an instructor at the University of Paris-Saclay, pursuing a PhD in quantum physics.",
        "education": "University of Paris-Saclay, PhD in Theoretical Physics, 2015; Ecole Normale Superieur, MA in Condensed Matter Physics, 2011",
        "expertise": ["Explainable machine learning", "Natural language processing", "Deep learning"]
      }
    ],
    "faculty_emeritus": [
      {
        "name": "Terence Parr",
        "email": "parrt@cs.usfca.edu",
        "office_location": "101 Howard 607",
        "description": "Terence is a professor of computer science and is the creator of the ANTLR parser generator. He herded programmers and implemented the large jGuru developers web site, during which time he developed and refined the StringTemplate engine.",
        "education": "Purdue University, PhD in Computer Engineering, 1993; University of Minnesota, Postdoctoral Fellow at the Army High-Performance Computing Research Center",
        "expertise": ["Software engineering", "Programming language design and implementation", "How programmers communicate with machines to build new software"]
      }
    ],
    "visiting_faculty": [
      {
        "name": "Nathaniel Stevens",
        "email": "ntstevens@usfca.edu",
        "description": "Nathaniel is interested in using data to make decisions, solve problems, and improve processes. Specifically, his research interests lie in methodological development at the intersection of data science and industrial statistics.",
        "education": "PhD, Statistics, University of Waterloo, 2015; MMATH, Statistics, University of Waterloo, 2011; BMATH, Statistics, University of Waterloo, 2010",
        "expertise": ["Experimental design", "A/B testing", "Social network modeling", "Survival and reliability analysis"]
      }
    ],
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "Can students participate in research with faculty members?",
        "answer": "Dr. Yannet Interian is an associate professor in the MSDS program with research interests in applying machine learning and deep learning to medical data. Students interested in collaborating on research projects with Dr. Interian are encouraged to reach out to her directly to discuss potential opportunities."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Student Employment": {
    "assistantships": "none available",
    "outside_work": "not recommended due to program intensity",
    "recommendation": "focus fully on program",
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "Are there teaching or research assistantships available?",
        "answer": "No, the MSDS program does not offer teaching or research assistantships."
      },
      {
        "question": "Can students work while in the program?",
        "answer": "The MSDS is an accelerated one-year program with a required practical training component, leaving little to no time for outside employment. Students are advised to focus fully on the program during their enrollment."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Student Services": {
    "health_insurance": {
      "enrollment": "automatic for 6+ units",
      "cost": 4100,
      "waiver": "available with proof of comparable insurance"
    },
    "qa_pairs": [
      {
        "question": "What health insurance requirements apply to students?",
        "answer": "Graduate students registered for 6 or more units are automatically enrolled in the USF-sponsored health insurance plan, costing approximately $4,100. Students with existing health coverage may waive this fee by providing proof of comparable insurance."
      }
    ]
  },
  "Curriculum": {
    "core_programming": [
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 501",
        "course_name": "Computation for Data Science",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "An intense review of Python programming and an introduction to a variety of computational problems."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 689",
        "course_name": "Data Structures and Algorithms",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "This course gives students a comprehensive view of data structures and algorithms."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 694",
        "course_name": "Distributed Computing",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "Students learn the MapReduce technique of distributed computing."
      }
    ],
    "statistics_mathematics": [
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 504",
        "course_name": "Review Probability and Stats",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "A review of random variables, moments, and maximum likelihood estimation."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 601",
        "course_name": "Linear Regression Analysis",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "This course is an intensive introduction to linear models."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 604",
        "course_name": "Time Series Analysis",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "This course is an intensive introduction to the existing methods for time series forecasting."
      }
    ],
    "machine_learning": [
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 621",
        "course_name": "Intro to Machine Learning",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "This course focuses on the implementation and application of supervised and unsupervised machine learning algorithms."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 630",
        "course_name": "Advanced Machine Learning",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "Students study advanced machine learning algorithms."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 634",
        "course_name": "Deep Learning",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "This course introduces students to a range of topics and concepts in deep learning."
      }
    ],
    "data_management": [
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 691",
        "course_name": "Relational Databases",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "This course aims to develop a strong understanding of relational database concepts."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 692",
        "course_name": "Data Acquisition",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "This lab-heavy Python class teaches students how to collect, merge, and clean data from multiple sources."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 697",
        "course_name": "Distributed Data Systems",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "Students study key-value store through NoSQL with a focus on using MongoDB."
      }
    ],
    "professional_skills": [
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 610",
        "course_name": "Communication for Data Science",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "Students will learn essential concepts related to business communication."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 603",
        "course_name": "Data Science Entrepreneurship",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "Students develop a minimum viable data science product."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 633",
        "course_name": "Ethics in Data Science",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "This course introduces ethical and privacy problems in data collection, algorithms, and evaluation."
      }
    ],
    "practicum_series": [
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 605",
        "course_name": "Data Science Practicum I",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "The data science practicum is a data science project sponsored by a company and mentored by a faculty member."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 625",
        "course_name": "Data Science Practicum II",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "Continuation of practicum series."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 627",
        "course_name": "Data Science Practicum III",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "Continuation of practicum series."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 632",
        "course_name": "Data Science Practicum IV",
        "units": 1,
        "description": "Final part of practicum series."
      }
    ],
    "data_engineering": [
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 680",
        "course_name": "Machine Learning Operations",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "The objective of this course is to learn the different stages of the end-to-end Machine Learning pipeline, from model development experiment tracking, all the way to model serving and model monitoring. For each step in the pipeline, students explore practical real world use cases and get hands-on experience with open source tools."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 681",
        "course_name": "Data Lakehouse",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "This course helps students understand the data lakehouse architecture, which enables the storage of raw, structured, and unstructured data for business analytics and machine learning."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 682",
        "course_name": "Data Stream Processing",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "This class equips students with the skills necessary to process continuous data streams at scale and in real-time."
      },
      {
        "course_id": "MSDS 683",
        "course_name": "Data Architecture",
        "units": 2,
        "description": "In this course, the students will earn the skill sets to understand the business applications, problems, and needs and design and organize data assets using data structures, storage, processing platforms, etc., accordingly to provide desirable efficiency, reliability, and security."
      }
    ]
  }
}